

Mohamed Yassin Rabie

Over a 18 year career in tech, working in different roles across different areas starting from initiation till delivery I have played different effective roles in development, solution design, team leadership, project, service management and finally IT strategy and enterprise architecture. I always seek not only to achieve and succeed but also to keep impact and realize value for my organization in technology, process and people.

0

https://www.linkedin.com/in/mohamed-yassin-4745158b/

Eng.yassin.1983@gmail.com

"□" +966 530605221

WORK EXPERIENCE

Enterprise Architect

12/2022 - Present

SPL

I am proud to be part of SPL digital transformation journey. By participating in the following EA office activities:

Creating IT Strategy Plan

- EA Principles

EA Tool assessment and selection criteria

AS IS State

- Gap analysis

Target State

Initiatives

- TRB

Make or Buy analysis

Development Team Lead

08/2021 - 11/2022

SPL

Leading +20 team members day by day activities to delivery high quality and ontime deliverables based on a clear road map.

Team structure

5 Backend developers

4 Mobile app developers

3 Integration developers

3 Frontend developers

3 SME

- 1 BA 2 QA

Different architectures [Monolith – NTier – SOA – Microservices]

Different technologies [Microsoft stack – non-microsoft]

Delivered in different hosting [cloud/inprems]

Standup daily meeting - DevOps - CI/CD

Code review / Unit Testing / Bench Marking / Health checks

Software Solution Consultant

06/2018 - 07/2021

Perfect Presentation [2P]

Solution design and guidance for different e-services and platforms.

Senior Software developer

07/2015 - 05/2018

Jeraisy

I have participated with teams to develop different web projects.

Software Web developer

06/2009 - 05/2015

Arabic Computer Systems - NTG

I have participated with teams to develop different web projects.

Software Web developer

02/2007 - 05/2009

EBLA Consultancy

I have participated with teams to archiving solutions .

Junior Software developer

01/2006 - 01/2007

EgyptNetwork

I have participated with teams to develop/support different SMS /CMS web portals

ACADEMIC BACKGROUND

2005 - Bachelor of Computer Science - Mansoura University -Egypt

LANGUAGES

English Arabic

CERTIFICATES

TOGAF - Enterprise Architecture PMP/ Project+ Project Management ITIL - IT Service Management

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

Here I am highlighting the different areas of my expertise, knowledge and used tools in the ALM

DEVELOPMENT

Backend: C#,vb.net,NODEJS ASP.Net/wcf/web -rest apis

Message brokers: rabbitmq/apache kafka/msmq

DATABASES: Ms sql/mysql/oracle -MongoDb-REDIS-solr

Caching: Redis/memory optimized tables

Realtime: socketio/Signalr

Background: scheduled /windows services/hangfire/pm2

Frontend:Angularjs-reactJS-js-html-css

Mobile:ionic /cordova/flutter

TESTING

functional /Non-functional testing

Test cases/scenarios

Tools: unit testing -Apache jmetre -Selenium



Mohamed Yassin Rabie

E-SERVICES, PROJECTS AND STATISTICS

SPL Last Mile Platform

Modenization from monolithic to microservices with event driven architecture.

Net Core - RabbitMQ - MS SQL Servers - SignalR

- +25K shipments /Day
- +470M transactions
- +3K users
- +45M shipments

CRM

- +9M Customers
- +3.3M SR E-POBox income
- +1.1B SR POBox income
- +1.5B SR NA registration income

Payment Gateway

- +9.7M Bills
- +321M SR payments
- +200K/H concurrent hit

Billing

- +33M Bills
- +5.2B SR Collected payment
- +50K bills/Day

Makani

- +177M SR income
- +1.6M tickets

ALAMI address forwarding

- +48M SR income
- 8K orders

E-Gov documents delivery services

- +11M orders
- 192M SR income

Notifications

- +50K SMS/Day
- 12K Chatbot notification/Day

Store2Door.com

FedEx SMSA international shipping customer portal

Al-RAJHI BANK Security system

sensors and monitoring cameras security management system

EgyptSMS.com / Nemra1.com

Capable to handle +100M SMS per day

REFERENCES

- Mushtag Baroad -IT Strategy & EAO Director
 - octor "=" 050000000
- Sami Alhedan e-Services and application Director "☐" 0500880023
- Majed Anzan Digital Transformation Director
- ° 0553366455

- ° 0582232725

SOLUTION DESIGN

Handled different architecture Microservices/ SOA/ ntier and monolithic solutions - physical and logical architecture with segregation of zones - Vast experience in Non-functional design requirement and solutions - experienced in design patters — SAAS - In-prem / Cloud (azure-aws)

Tools: drawio/visio

ANALYSIS

Define problem statement – propose solutions and alternatives -

BRD-SRS / user stories

Traceability matrix

IT SERVICE MANAGEMENT

incident management systems and flows

- Launched weekly CAB-DevOps

Experienced in disaster management and hyper care status reporting

Operation Monitoring tools ELK logging /uptime/Riverbed

ITIL certified

IT PROJECT MANAGEMENT

Prepared RFI, RFP and assessment and evaluation criteria and scoring.

Managing time/scheduled and effort estimation - Resources/team conflict Management - Waterfall-Agile methodologies - Procurement /make or buy analysis - Risk register/monitor and mitigation plan.

PMP certified/Project+

EA OFFICE &

DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION

Prepared IT strategic plan

Created initiatives on tech/people and process -Define AS IS /Gap analysis/ Target - business and technical capabilities - Launched weekly TRB

TOGAF certified

PERSONAL INFO

Married - DOB: 04th of July 1983